The fundamental root of it all building block for linear algebra is the vector.
线性代数所有知识都是建立在向量这个基础上的
So, it's worth making sure that we're all on
所以向量到底是什么
the same page about what exactly a vector is.
我们有必要就这点达成一致
You see, broadly speaking,
广义上说
there are three distinct but related ideas about vectors,
人们对向量有三种相互区别但又相互联系的看法
which I'll call the physics student perspective,
我分别称为物理学学生视角
the computer science student perspective and the mathematician perspective.
计算机科学学生视角以及数学家视角
The physics student perspective is that vectors are arrows pointing in space.
在物理学学生的眼中 向量是空间里的箭头
What defines a given vector,
定义向量的
is its length and the direction it's pointing.
是其长度和所指方向
But as long as those two facts are the same,
只要保持这两个属性相同
you can move it all around and it's still the same vector.
你可以随意移动向量 向量本身不会发生变化
Vectors that live in the flat plane,
平面中的向量
are two-dimensional and those sitting in broader space,
是二维的 但你和我所在的更高维空间
that you and I live in, are three-dimensional.
也有向量 这些向量是三维的
The computer science perspective is that vectors are ordered lists of numbers.
从计算机科学的角度看 向量是有序的数值列表
For example, let's say you were doing some analytics about house prices,
比如 假设你要分析房价
and the only features you cared about were square footage and price.
而且你只想研究房屋面积和价格
You might model each house with a pair of numbers,
你可能会用一对数字给各房子建模
the first indicating square footage and the second indicating price.
第一个数字表示房屋面积 第二个数字表示价格
Notice, the order matters here.
注意 这里的顺序是有意义的
In the lingo, you'd be modeling houses as two-dimensional vectors,
专业点讲 你是在用二维向量给房子建模
where in this context vector is pretty much just a fancy word for list,
此时 “向量” 其实就是 “列表” 好听些的说法
and what makes it two-dimensional,
而向量之所以是二维的
is the fact that the length of that list is two.
是因为列表的长度为 2
The mathematician, on the other hand,
而数学家
seeks to generalize both these views,
则综合了上述两种观点
basically saying that a vector can be anything
认为向量可以是任何事物
where there's a sensible notion of adding two vectors,
只要能对其进行加法运算
and multiplying a vector by a number,
以及能将其与数字相乘即可
operations that I'll talk about later on in this video.
稍后我会进一步讲解这些运算
The details of this view are rather abstract,
数学视角其实没那么具体 比较抽象
but the reason they bring it up here,
但之所以要讲数学视角
is that it hints at the fact that the ideas of
是因为该视角暗示了一个事实
vector addition and multiplication by numbers,
即向量加法或数字与向量的乘法
will play an important role throughout linear algebra.
贯穿线性代数始终
But before we talk about those operations,
但在我们讲解这些运算之前
let's just settle in on a specific thought to have in mind,
我们先确定
when I say the word vector.
当我提 “向量” 这个词时 指的是什么
Given the geometric focus that I'm shooting for here,
由于本视频重在图像概念
whenever we introduce a new topic involving vectors,
所以无论我谈起什么涉及向量的话题
I want you to first think about an arrow, and specifically,
我希望你能先把向量想成一个箭头
think about that arrow inside a coordinate system,
更具体地讲 是把向量想成一个位于坐标系的箭头
like the x, y plane,
比如 xy 坐标系
with its tail sitting at the origin.
并想象向量的尾部在原点上
This is a little bit different from the physics student perspective,
这与物理学学生的视角有些区别
where vectors can freely sit anywhere they want in space.
如果从物理视角出发 向量可以落在空间里的任意位置
In linear algebra, it's almost always
但在线性代数中
the case that your vector will be rooted at the origin.
向量基本都是从原点出发的
Then, once you understand a new concept in the context of arrows in space,
等你借助空间箭头理解了新概念
we'll translate it over to the list of numbers point of view,
你就可以把箭头想成数值列表
which we can do by considering the coordinates of the vector.
也就是以向量坐标的角度来思考问题了
Now, while I'm sure that many of you are already familiar with this coordinate system,
虽然我知道你们大多数人都很熟悉这个坐标系了
it's worth walking through explicitly,
但我觉得有必要再具体讲讲
since this is where all of the important back and
因为能在线性代数两种视角之间来回切换是很重要的
forth happens between the two perspectives of linear algebra.
而这正是切换的关键所在